{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "During this battle, Uluc¸ [oo-looch] Ali was able to capture the standard of the Knights Hospitaller. The Genoese admiral Andrea Doria fought in this battle after a defeat at the Battle of Preveza. Six powerful galleasses were provided by Venice to this battle’s winning side, which was commanded by Don John, the brother of the Holy Roman Emperor Philip II. For ten points, name this decisive 1571 naval victory for a Christian alliance, stopping the Ottoman advance into the Mediterranean Sea.",
      "answer": "Battle of Lepanto"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer set texts from the Book of Revelation in a piece celebrating victory in the Franco- Prussian War, his Triumphlied. He quoted “Der Landesvater” and the drinking song “Gaudeamus Igitur” in a piece written to celebrate an honorary doctorate from the University of Breslau. Hans von Bulow called this man’s first symphony “Beethoven’s Tenth.” The Academic Festival Overture was written by, for ten points, what German composer whose Wiegenlied [vee-gen-leed] is known as his “Lullaby?”",
      "answer": "Johannes Brahms"
    },
    {
      "question": "Major John Brown’s failure to reinforce this man’s army in time resulted in Guy Carleton’s capture of this man at the Battle of Longue-Pointe. The day before Seth Warner took Fort Crown Point, this man and Benedict Arnold led a successful capture of a fort whose weapons helped end the Siege of Boston. Fort Ticonderoga was captured by, for ten points, what leader of Vermont’s Green Mountain Boys?",
      "answer": "Ethan Allen"
    },
    {
      "question": "A myth relates how this location was created after a king performed a thousand years of penance to break a curse on 60,000 brothers who had been incinerated. Millions of people journeyed to this location in February 2013 as part of a Kumbh Mela pilgrimage whose final destination was in Allahabad. Waters in this location are said to have purifying powers because they have touched Vishnu’s feet. For ten points, name this sacred river of Hinduism.",
      "answer": [
        "Ganges River",
        "Ganga",
        "Allahabad before read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "As Chancellor of the Exchequer, this politician introduced a budget that included the Cobden- Chevalier Treaty, lowering Anglo-French tariffs. As Prime Minister, he was able to secure the passage of a bill which benefited Irish tenants, but was never able to secure home rule during his four terms. This man’s Midlothian Campaign attacked his rival, a Conservative politician with a close friendship with Queen Victoria. For ten points, name this Liberal Prime Minister who feuded with Benjamin Disraeli.",
      "answer": "William Ewart Gladstone"
    },
    {
      "question": "This building was the site of an infamous jump by Franz Reichelt, whose parachute demonstration failed. This structure was derided as a “gigantic black smokestack” in a petition by the “Artists Protest,” which attempted to stop its construction. Maurice Koechlin and Emile Nouguier helped design this structure, found on the Champ de Mars, for the World’s Fair of 1889. For ten points, name this iconic wrought iron tower in Paris.",
      "answer": "Eiffel Tower"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. The construction of this location at Mount Li was described by Sima Qian [chee-ahn], who noted that streams of mercury flowed through it in an attempt to recreate the Yangtze and Yellow Rivers. This location was first discovered by workers digging a well in Xiyang [shee-yahng]. To serve their master in the afterlife, thousands of terracotta warriors were placed in, for ten points, what resting place of the first emperor of unified China?",
      "answer": [
        "The Mausoleum of the First Qin Emperor",
        "descriptions of Qin Shi Huangdi’s mausoleum",
        "Qin Shi Huangdi in place of “Qin",
        "”",
        "equivalents for mausoleum, such as tomb, burial ground, grave, etc"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This program gained support after a report by Herbert Hoover deemed it was infeasible to turn one nation into a “pastoral state” without the migration of 25 million people. This program, which replaced the punitive Morgenthau Plan, was announced at a Harvard commencement speech in 1947. Greece and Turkey received the first part of a disbursement of 13 billion dollars under, for ten points, what American foreign policy to help rebuild postwar Europe, named for the US Secretary of State?",
      "answer": [
        "Marshall Plan",
        "European Recovery Program",
        "ERP"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A medieval philosopher from this country was the first Westerner to record the formula for gunpowder in his Opus Majus. Another medieval philosopher from this country developed a “law of parsimony” that seeks to solve problems by working with the hypothesis with the fewest assumptions; that “razor” was developed by William of Ockham. For ten points, name this home country of Roger Bacon where medieval scholars studied at the University of Oxford.",
      "answer": "England"
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization partially titles the autobiography of its one-time leading member, George Plunkitt. This group aided the gubernatorial campaign of John Hoffman, one of its leaders known as Grand Sachems. This organization, which declined after the mayoral election of Fiorello La Guardia in 1934, achieved notoriety for its corruption and abuse of the spoils system under Boss Tweed. For ten points, name this New York City political machine.",
      "answer": "Tammany Hall"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Bob Dylan refused to appear on this show when network officials asked him to not play “Talkin’ John Birch Paranoid Blues.” This show displayed the caption “SORRY GIRLS, HE’S MARRIED” on February 9, 1964. Charles Laughton filled in as host of this show on the first night that this show featured Elvis Presley, although this show’s cameramen zoomed in to avoid broadcasting Elvis’s provocative dancing. For ten points, name this CBS show that ran until 1971 and which drew over 70 million viewers for its first broadcast of The Beatles.",
        "answer": "The Ed Sullivan Show"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "For the Beatles’ first appearance, Ed Sullivan noted that a telegraph of support had come in from Elvis and this man, his longtime manager.",
        "answer": [
          "Colonel Tom Parker",
          "Thomas Andrew Parker",
          "Andreas Cornelis van Kujik"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one speech, this man was accused of turning ministers into marionnettes by Vladimir Purishkevich, who soon agreed to aid Prince Felix Yusupov in putting this man to death. This man rose to power after providing medical guidance to Alexandra Feodorovna [fay-oh-dor-ohv-na], but this man was eventually poisoned, beaten, shot, and then drowned by nobles who believed he had undue influence over the Romanov family. For ten points, name this Russian mystic and advisor to Nicholas II.",
        "answer": "Grigori Rasputin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Rasputin’s medical advice concerned the hemophilia suffered by this son of Alexandra and Nicholas II. This brother of Olga, Tatiana, Maria, and Anastasia died in the 1918 execution of the Romanovs.",
        "answer": "Alexei Nikolaevich Romanov"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This location experienced a population surge after the Battle of White Marsh. At this location, a work on “Regulations for the Order and Discipline” was translated into the “Blue Book.” One general’s inaction while at this location led to the Conway Cabal plot, which aimed to replace him with Horatio Gates. For ten points, name this location that served as Washington’s winter quarters for the Continental Army from 1777 to 1778.",
        "answer": "Valley Forge"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Prussian officer wrote the aforementioned “Blue Book” and trained the American army as Washington’s inspector general.",
        "answer": [
          "Baron von Steuben",
          "Friedrich Wilhelm von Steuben"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler created an administrative system with 33 ranks and a standardized system of payment called the mansabdari system. This ruler, who was advised by the Nine Jewels, created the House of Worship for discussions between different religious leaders. The Din-i-Ilahi syncretic religion, founded by this ruler, replaced Islam as the state religion. This son of Humayun defeated the Hindu king Hemu at the Second Battle of Panipat. For ten points, name this third Mughal emperor, the grandson of Babur.",
        "answer": "Akbar the Great"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Akbar’s policies of religious toleration included a temporary end to this tax, which was levied on non-Muslims. Later Mughal rulers resumed this tax.",
        "answer": "jizya tax"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The god Mithras is often portrayed sacrificing one of these animals in reliefs, such as one in Vienna’s Kunsthistoriches Museum. A woman holding pink fabric grabs onto a swimming, white one of these animals in Titian’s Rape of Europa. In Hindu myth, Shiva’s mount is one of these animals named Nandi. Scenes from frescos found at the Palace of Knossos depict youths jumping over the horns of, for ten points, what bovine animal represented by the constellation Taurus?",
        "answer": "bulls"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A “Hall” of bulls, which probably shows many paintings of the extinct aurochs, is a chamber at this prehistoric site in southwestern France that was rediscovered by children in 1940.",
        "answer": "Lascaux caves"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Aulus Hirtius and Vibius Pansa died while fighting against this man’s army, which was busy besieging Decimus Brutus at Mutina. This man, who split his territory between his children in the Donations of Alexandria, was the third and final husband of Fulvia. In 31 BC, this man fled from the Battle of Actium after the retreat of his lover, Cleopatra. For ten points, name this protege of Julius Caesar who lost a civil war to Octavian.",
        "answer": "Mark Antony or Marcus Antonius"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the aforementioned Donations of Alexandria, Marc Antony gave control of Egypt to Cleopatra and this man, a son of Cleopatra and Julius Caesar, who ultimately served as the last pharaoh of Egypt.",
        "answer": [
          "Caesarion",
          "Ptolemy XV Caesar, but do not"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A leader of one of these organizations, Dave Beck, pled the Fifth Amendment when he was called to testify in front of the McClellan Committee. Voting procedures in these organizations are governed by the Landrum-Griffin Act. Agreements whereby people vowed not to join these organizations, or yellow dog contracts, were outlawed by the Norris-LaGuardia Act. For ten points, name these organizations that may engage in collective bargaining with management on behalf of their working members.",
        "answer": [
          "labor unions",
          "Teamsters during the first sentence"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Currently, 28 states have passed this type of law prohibiting contracts or hiring conditions that compel workers to join unions. Some opponents of this type of law note that its three-word name is misleading.",
        "answer": "right-to-work law"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This character says that “a good heart” is more like the sun than the moon because it always shines brightly; that speech woos his future wife, who returns his affections in French because she cannot speak English. This character, who announces “Once more unto the breach, dear friends” at the siege of Harfleur, urges “We few, we happy few, we band of brothers” into battle in a fourth act speech. For ten points, name this Shakespearean character, an English king who marries Catherine of Valois after winning at Agincourt.",
        "answer": "Henry V"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The “We band of brothers” quote derives from this Act IV speech, given by Henry V as his army prepares to fight the Battle of Agincourt.",
        "answer": "Saint Crispin’s Day speech"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The First US Congress",
      "prompt": "Name the the first us congress...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City whose Federal Hall hosted its first two sessions, as well as Washington’s inauguration.",
          "answer": "New York City or NYC"
        },
        {
          "question": "Set of the first ten Constitutional amendments, introduced in the House in 1789.",
          "answer": "Bill of Rights"
        },
        {
          "question": "Representative and future President who introduced those amendments.",
          "answer": "James Madison"
        },
        {
          "question": "State with the largest House delegation, including that future President.",
          "answer": "Virginia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Branch of the Armed Forces established in 1790 as the Revenue-Marine, a customs enforcement service.",
          "answer": "US Coast Guard"
        },
        {
          "question": "Retired general confirmed as Secretary of War in 1789.",
          "answer": "Henry Knox"
        },
        {
          "question": "State whose first Congressional delegation included Robert Morris and Speaker Frederick Muhlenberg.",
          "answer": "Pennsylvania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Author of the Judiciary Act of 1789, a Connecticut Senator who was later Chief Justice.",
          "answer": "Oliver Ellsworth"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Russian Vocabulary",
      "prompt": "Give the Russian term for...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The main government complex in Moscow, as well as a type of fortress in general.",
          "answer": "Kremlin"
        },
        {
          "question": "ThefactionthatsplitfromtheMensheviksintheRussianRevolution,fromtheRussianfor“majority.”",
          "answer": "Bolsheviks"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Restructuring,” that paired with “glasnost” as a means of reform in the late Soviet Union.",
          "answer": "perestroika"
        },
        {
          "question": "A Soviet prison labor camp, derived from an acronym for the system.",
          "answer": "gulag"
        },
        {
          "question": "A former newspaper of the Communist Party whose name translates to “Truth.”",
          "answer": "Pravda"
        },
        {
          "question": "Damaging material used to blackmail political opponents.",
          "answer": "kompromat"
        },
        {
          "question": "The loyal police force of Ivan the Terrible, who killed thousands in Novgorod.",
          "answer": [
            "Oprichniki",
            "Oprichnina",
            "Oprichniks"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "A seasonal second cottage in the countryside, gifted to party officials in the Soviet Union.",
          "answer": "dacha"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Israel",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Holy city that Israel claims as its capital, recognized by Donald Trump in 2017.",
          "answer": "Jerusalem"
        },
        {
          "question": "Financial capital of Israel, the city where most countries maintain their embassies.",
          "answer": "Tel Aviv"
        },
        {
          "question": "Empire that governed Israel as the province of Judea.",
          "answer": "Roman Empire or Rome"
        },
        {
          "question": "Unicameral legislative body of Israel.",
          "answer": "Knesset"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Iron Lady” of Israel who served as its fourth Prime Minister.",
          "answer": [
            "Golda Meir",
            "Golda Myerson",
            "Golda Mabovitch"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Organizer of the IDF who served as the first Prime Minister of Israel.",
          "answer": "David Ben-Gurion"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ugandan airport where Israel Defense Forces rescued over 100 hostages in 1976.",
          "answer": [
            "Entebbe International Airport",
            "Entebbe Raid, etc."
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Father of modern Zionism who published The Jewish State and advocated a Jewish homeland in Uganda.",
          "answer": "Theodor Herzl"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This river was the site of the second largest flood in geologic history, the Bonneville flood, when the Portneuf River overflowed into this river during the last ice age. This river derived its name from a misinterpreted (20 pts)",
        "Shoshone hand signal for the nearby abundant salmon, the letter S. This river flows through Twin Falls, north of which (10 pts)",
        "Evel Knievel failed to jump across a canyon in 1974. For ten points, name this tributary of the Columbia that flows past Boise to form the northern border between Idaho and Oregon."
      ],
      "answer": "Snake River"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this modern day country, Johann Beaulieu was unable to defend a bridgehead over the river Adda at Lodi [loh-dee]; this set-back, along with Joseph Alvinzci’s defeat at Arcole [ar-co-lay] in this modern day country, ensured that the First (20 pts)",
        "Coalition would have to accept the creation of the Ligurian Republic. Another battle in this modern day country, the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Marengo, began when a commander led his troops atop a donkey through the St. Bernard Pass. For ten points, name this modern-day country where Napoleon crossed the Alps to score a victory near Piedmont."
      ],
      "answer": "Italy"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In October 2016, an attack against these people in Maungdaw was carried out by Harakah al-Yaqin insurgents. A government began resettling this group to the manmade island of Thengar Char in January 2017, much to the dismay of (20 pts)",
        "human rights groups. The United Nations said it was “very likely” that crimes against humanity were taking place against these people, who primarily live in (10 pts)",
        "Rakhine State, north of the Bay of Bengal. Aung San Suu Kyi [chee] has been heavily criticized for her silence on the persecution of, for ten points, what Muslim ethnic group that primarily lives in Burma?"
      ],
      "answer": "Rohingya people"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this election year, the losing ticket’s vice presidential nominee developed the recurring theme of the “Two Americas;” that politician then lost his position as Senator from North Carolina. After this election year’s (20 pts)",
        "Iowa caucuses, the third-place finisher shouted “Yeah!” at the end of his rallying speech; that shriek by Howard Dean is largely thought to have doomed his campaign. (10 pts)",
        "Veterans used “swiftboating” to attack the Democratic nominee in this year. For ten points, name this year in which John Edwards and John Kerry lost to the re-election campaign of George W. Bush."
      ],
      "answer": "U.S. Presidential Election of 2004"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A leader of this country created a complex system of telex machines in Operation Cybersyn, a plan to aid his economic planning. That leader of this country gained controversy for nationalizing the (20 pts)",
        "copper industry, and later committed suicide in La Moneda Palace after a successful coup against him. Another ruler of this country implemented neoliberal economic policies with the help of the (10 pts)",
        "“Chicago Boys” and, with CIA backing, brutally suppressed political dissent in Operation Condor. For ten points, name this South American country once ruled by Salvador Allende and Augusto Pinochet."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Chile"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1946, this figure noted “there is a somber point in the social outlook of Americans” in a lecture against racism at the historically black Lincoln University. This figure’s literary rights were bequeathed to the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, which he helped establish. This man (20 pts)",
        "signed a 1939 letter written by Leo Szilard [zee-lard] that was sent to President Roosevelt, warning him of the threat of (10 pts)",
        "German nuclear bombs. For ten points, name this physicist who won a Nobel Prize for his work on the photoelectric effect and who also developed the theory of special relativity."
      ],
      "answer": "Albert Einstein"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first instance of NATO active combat occurred during this war’s Banja Luka incident, part of Operation Deny Flight. Signs reading “pazi,” meaning “watch out,” were put up in “Sniper (20 pts)",
        "Alley” during this war. Ratko Mladic [m’lah-ditch] was convicted of crimes against humanity for his command during the Srebrenica [sreh-breh-neet-zah] Massacre during this war, which was ended by the (10 pts)",
        "Dayton Agreement in 1995. For ten points, name this war during the breakup of Yugoslavia that included the Siege of Sarajevo."
      ],
      "answer": "Bosnian War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was the first African American to be honored with a national memorial, placed in Diamond, Missouri. This man gained fame overnight after he testified in 1921 Congressional tariff hearings. This man, who advertised a massage oil (20 pts)",
        "cure for polio in the 1930s, promoted the cultivation of legumes and (10 pts)",
        "sweet potatoes in the South to alternate with cotton farming. For ten points, name this agricultural researcher at the Tuskegee Institute who developed numerous peanut-based products, but did not actually invent peanut butter."
      ],
      "answer": "George Washington Carver"
    }
  ]
}